Nilkumar Patel

nilkumar-patel.com github.com/nsptel linkedin.com/in/nsptel +1(647)914-8448 nilkumarpatel48@gmail.com Toronto, ON

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

An enthusiastic, accomplished, and self-motivated individual with great software engineering skills, strong understanding in working of any modern software architecture, and deep interest in new IT developments. With two years of professional Software Engineering experience, has exceptional interpersonal, analytical, and problem-solving skills, with a positive and adaptive attitude.

EXPERIENCE

SimplifyVMS, Toronto, ON

June 2023 - Present

Full Stack Engineer (Angular, Django, MySQL, AWS)

Working with a cross-functional team using emerging technologies and following best practices to deliver a software service used by large enterprises.

- Developing reliable core APIs while maintaining security and performance of the overall backend architecture.
- Optimizing database schemas, queries, and data models for efficient storage, retrieval, and manipulation of information.
- Designing better UI by following industry and organizational standards, and efficiently improving user experience.
- Understanding a multi-tenant vendor management system to tackle data related risks and participating in regular meetings to stay informed about client feedback.
- Troubleshooting and resolving software defects, performance bottlenecks, and technical issues, ensuring timely resolution to minimize disruptions in system functionality.

FreshBooks, Toronto, ON 🛂

November 2021 - March 2023

Software Engineer (EmberJS, Flask, GCP)

Collaborated with a team of six Software Engineers, a Product Manager and a Designer, to improve and maintain an existing accounting software's customer-centric UI, and to contribute to the development of a new organizational translation service.

- Developed a language translation service by following hexagonal architecture resulting in a central repository where tools such as Google Cloud PubSub and CloudSQL are used.
- Led an initiative for performance optimization which resulted in front-end bundle size reduction of over 18%, and faster First Contentful Paint times.
- Made CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins that ensured best workflow, continuous deployment and concentrated on exhaustive testing using various tools like PyTest, QUnit, Cucumber, etc.
- Helped in analytics and created alerts using monitoring tools such as Datadog, which reduced the organization's incident report times and thus, provided 99.98% uptime on average every quarter.
- Managed to make the web application more accessible (91% compliance in Level Access audit) and made internationalization easier to implement through an external service.
- Helped interns get on board and provided support for starting their journey.

EDUCATION

Post-graduate Diploma - Confederation College, 2021

Major: Information Communication Technology for Small Businesses | GPA: 4.0

Skills Learned: Full Stack Web Development, Mobile Application Development, Database Management

Bachelor of Engineering - Gujarat Technological University, 2019

Major: Computer Engineering | GPA: 4.0 (CGPA: 8.48)

Skills Learned: Data Structures and Algorithms, Computer Programming, Object-Oriented Programming

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Core: Python, JavaScript, Java (J2EE), C, C++

• Web: Angular, Django, React, Ember, Flask, TypeScript, Tailwind, Sass, Next, PHP

• Mobile: React Native

• Databases: MySQL, MongoDB, Firestore

Other: Git, Docker, Jenkins, GCP, AWS, Datadog, Jira

PROJECTS

Cricketable (React Native, Firebase) Github

May 2021 - Aug 2021 (Confederation College)

Developed a mobile application that works on Android and iOS using React Native Framework with two other students. This application is used for connecting people, setting up groups and organizing events for people who share interest in the game of Cricket.

SQL Query Executor for Excel Sheets (Python, MySQL) Github

July 2018 - April 2019 (Gujarat Technological University)

Crafted a Windows desktop application using Python (TKinter, ExcelRD) which had great user-experience and flow. This tool was used for executing SQL selection queries on Excel spreadsheets and making the data extraction process easy and efficient.

AWARDS AND CERTIFICATIONS

- Received scholarship grant from Confederation College for persistent studies and regular involvement in extracurricular activities (Jan 2021).
- Ranked first out of 42 candidates in Web Weaver, a zonal web development competition organized by Gujarat Technological University (Sept 2018).